Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף Daf is פ"ט Phet-Tet 189
we pick up with the משנה Mishna at the bottom of פ"ח
עמוד ב' Phet-Chet Amud Bet about ten lines from the bottom. חומר
בדברי סופרים מדברי תורה Chomer bedivrei sofrim midivrei torah in a way
things that are not rabbinic דברי סופרים Divrei sofrim here means a
rabbinic interpretation of the פסוקים Psukim can is weightier than the actual
things that are explicit in the פסוקים. Psukim. האומר אין תפילין כדי
לעבור על דברי תורה פטור Haomer ein tfillin kidei la'avor al divrei
torah patur if a זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre were to say there's
no such thing as תפילין Tfillin directly going against explicit פסוקים Psukim
in the תורה Torah he'd be פטור Patur because that's not a
הוראה Hora'ah זקן ממרא'ס Zaken Mamre's position himself as a פוסק Posek
in the defiance of בית דין Beis Din okay you'd be פטור
Patur that's not a הוראה. Hora'ah. חמש טוטפות להוסיף על דברי סופרים
חייב Chamesh totafos lehosif al divrei sofrim chayav however he says yes
there is תפילין Tfillin in the תורה Torah but it's not four
בתים Batim you know in the של ראש Shel Rosh it's five
בתים Batim then he is חייב Chayav that is a הוראה Hora'ah
and therefore you could be חייב Chayav so something that's less explicit
you're more חייב Chayav for because there's an element of פסקנ'ינג Paskening
where there is not in the first case. Let's take a look
at the גמרא Gemara by the way that makes it clear according
to this משנה Mishna not like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that you
do not need something that you are חייב Chayav like you know
that's about כרת Kares and חטאת Chatas and so on this is
the broader position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that anything constitutes you
know a זקן ממרא. Zaken Mamre. Okay אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi
Elazar said אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar אמר רבי אושעיה Amar
Rabbi Oshaya אינו חייב אלא על דבר שעיקרו מדברי תורה ופירושו מדברי
סופרים ויש בו להוסיף ואם הוסיף גורע. Eino chayav ela al davar
she'ikaro midivrei torah uperusho midivrei sofrim veyesh bo lehosif ve'im hosif goreiah.
Okay so he's making it much narrower you know than the משנה
Mishna our משנה Mishna gave תפילין Tfillin as an example but it
basically said anything that's not explicit. He is saying no the only
thing that a זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre is חייב Chayav for is
something that starts with something explicit in the תורה Torah but there's
an explanation but there's a rabbinic understanding of what the parameters are
okay that's still most of תורה Torah right what constitutes שבת Shabbos
what constitutes anything there's always a פירוש מדברי סופרים Perusho midivrei sofrim
ויש בו להוסיף Veyesh bo lehosif but here's where it gets very
narrow what you did is you added something that wasn't there ואם
הוסיף גורע Ve'im hosif goreiah but through adding it subtracted. Okay so
in our case of the משנה Mishna he said there was a
fifth בית Bayis but because he said there was a fifth בית
Bayis of you know of compartment of the תפילין Tfillin that made
the תפילין Tfillin פסול. Pasul. ואנו אין לנו אלא תפילין Va'anu ein
lanu ela tfillin and the only example would be the one case
in the משנה Mishna so before we said we had so many
examples of everything under the sun we're now going to take the
case in our משנה Mishna and say that is the only case.
And אליבא דרבי יהודה Aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda it's like רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda who said you know על פי התורה אשר יורוך Al pi
hatorah asher yoruha that it has to be תורה Torah something explicit
in the פסוקים Psukim and אשר יורוך Asher yoruha there has to
be an interpretation. Now again that would actually on the face of
it be even broader than רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir pretty much anything
that there's a תורה שבעל פה Torah sheba'al peh component to. But
he is adding this idea of להוסיף Lehosif and גורע Goreiah and
limiting it ממש Mamash just to the case
of
תפילין. Tfillin. Okay והאיכא לולב דעיקרו מדברי תורה ופירושו מדברי סופרים הבו
ליה לולב. Veha ika lulav de'ikaro midivrei torah uperusho midivrei sofrim habata
lulav. What are the מינים Minim in a לולב Lulav you know
that's also interpretation of חז"ל Chazal ויש בו להוסיף Veyesh bo lehosif
you could add if you added an extra מין Min you know
you would be adding to what the תורה Torah says ואם הוסיף
גורע Ve'im hosif goreiah and if you add you take off you
invalidate the ארבעה מינים. Arba Minim. So the גמרא Gemara says no
מאי סבירא ליה Mai svira leh what do you assume? אי סבירא
ליה דלולב אין צריך אגד Ei svira leh delulav ein tzarich egged
if you assume that the binding we make with the לולב Lulav
הדסים Hadassim and ערבות Aravos is not required in the תורה Torah
so האי לחודיה קאי והאי לחודיה קאי Hai lechudei kai vehai lechudei
kai even if you said there was an additional מין Min that
you had to add to the לולב Lulav and you know you
would not invalidate the לולב Lulav you might be עובר Over on
בל תוסיף Ba'al tosif when you took it if you took an
extra מין Min maybe yes maybe no it's not exactly clear what
we're talking about the עבירה Avera of בל תוסיף Ba'al tosif okay
maybe you say האי לחודיה קאי Hai lechudei kai and you're not
even being עובר Over on בל תוסיף Ba'al tosif but even if
you are because each one stands by itself you're not redefining the
מצווה Mitzva object and invalidating it so it's not מוסיף גורע. Mosif
goreiah.
ואי סבירא ליה דצריך אגד Vei svira leh detzarich egged now if
a לולב Lulav needs to be bound those three מינים Minim גרוע
ועומד הוא Garua ve'omed hu and you made a thing that included
לולב הדסים ערבות Lulav hadassim aravos and I don't know and a
palm and a you know an oak branch okay then that bundle
would already be an invalid bundle. It would be four pieces and
not three pieces and it would inherently be פסול Pasul to start
with as opposed to being כשר Kosher but the addition made it
פסול. Pasul. Now you're going to ask how is that any different
than the תפילין Tfillin so hold on we will see. Okay but
that never started as being good and became ungood from the very
moment it was bundled it was all invalid object.
והאיכא ציצית Veha ika tzitzis what about ציצית Tzitzis דעיקרו מדברי תורה.
De'ikaro midivrei torah. Again like pretty much everything, there's a rabbinic interpretation
part of this. ויש בל תוסיף, veyesh bal tosif, you can add,
if you add an extra string to your ציצית, tzitzis, right? ואם
הוסיף גורע, ve'im hosif gore'a, and if you do, you would invalidate
it. So the גמרא Gemara would say, one minute, but ציצית מאי
סבירא לן? tzitzis mai sevira lan? What do you assume? אי סבירא
לן דקשר עליון לאו דאורייתא, ei sevira lan dekesher elyon lav de'oraisa,
if you're assuming that the top knot is not דאורייתא, de'oraisa, which
nobody really assumes, but even if you were to argue that, היי
לחוד קאי והיי לחוד קאי. hai lechud kai vehai lechud kai. If
you had an extra string, okay, it would be standing by itself,
it wouldn't invalidate, it wouldn't redefine the מצוה mitzvah act. ואי סבירא
לן, ve'ei sevira lan, and if you hold, top of
פ''ט עמוד א', peis tes amud alef, דקשר העליון דאורייתא, dekesher ha'elyon
de'oraisa, the top knot is דאורייתא, de'oraisa, which is how we פוסקין,
pasken, גרוע ועומד. garu ve'omed. As soon as you made that first
knot, you'd have too many strings and it would be invalid. So
it wouldn't be something that would be כשר kosher and then the
addition made it invalid. It never started as כשר. kosher. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי תפילין נמי. ei hachi tefillin nami. So
the גמרא Gemara says the same by תפילין. tefillin. אי עביד ארבע
בתי, ei avid arba batei, if you started with four בתי batim
on your תפילין, tefillin, וסמכיה ואנחה גבייהו, vesamchei ve'an-chei gabaihu, and then
you made a fifth sort of compartment that you then stuck on
to the תפילין, tefillin, so היי לחוד קאי והיי לחוד קאי, hai
lechud kai vehai lechud kai, it's a separate unit and it doesn't
invalidate the what you have in your unit of four. Each one
stands by itself. דעביד חמישה בתי, de'avid chamisha batei, and if you
created initially a unit of five, גרוע ועומד הוא, garu ve'omed hu,
that's just like knotting extra strings in your טלית, tallis, in your
ציצית, tzitzis, or putting extra מינים minim in your לולב. lulav. You
start with something invalid. So how is this any different? אמר רב
זירא, amar Rav Zeira, בית חיצון שאינו רואה את
האוויר פסול. bayis chitzon she'eino ro'eh es ha'avir pasul. No, what made
it invalid is not the five per se, but you need the
outer
compartments to be exposed to the air. So when you added a
fifth compartment, even though it's היי לחוד קאי, hai lechud kai, so
it started כשר, kosher, you had four compartments, you added a fifth,
even though it's היי לחוד קאי, hai lechud kai, it doesn't redefine
it as a unit of five compartments, it invalidated it by not
making the outer compartment, the outer edge of the outer compartments, exposed
to the open air. All right, so that's
interesting, but it's not really at all clear why רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar makes this very very limited idea that it's not just it
needs a rabbinic component and based on a תורה, Torah, which is
what the משנה Mishnah says, but it actually needs this מוסיף גורע
mosif gore'a and so on, and why that's the definition of זקן
ממרא. zaken mamre. There's actually no פסוקים psukim or whatever are quoted
to explain that. Let's take a look at the next משנה Mishnah
continuing with זקן ממרא. zaken mamre. אין ממיתין אותו לא בבית דין
שבעירו ולא בבית דין שביבנה. ein memisin oso lo beveise din shebe'iro
velo beveise din shebeyavne. You don't execute him in his local בית
דין Beis Din or in the בית דין Beis Din in יבנה.
Yavne. רש''י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos try to figure out, why are
we mentioning the בית דין Beis Din in יבנה? Yavne? The בית
דין Beis Din in יבנה Yavne really only came to prominence after
there was no longer a בית דין Beis Din in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and you needed the בית דין Beis Din in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash for somebody to be a זקן ממרא.
zaken mamre. But okay, even in a major בית דין Beis Din
outside of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אלא מעלין אותו לבית דין
הגדול
שבירושלים. ela ma'alin oso leveise din hagadol shebirushalayim. There's only one place
to do this, his judgment, which is in the בית דין הגדול
שבירושלים. Beis Din Hagadol shebirushalayim. We know he has to reject their
ruling, but it's not enough that he rejects the ruling of the
בית דין הגדול שבירושלים, Beis Din Hagadol shebirushalayim, that's where you have
to have his גמר דין gmar din and that's where you have
to actually execute him. ומשמרים
אותו עד הרגל, umeshamrin oso ad haregel, you wait until it's a
רגל, regel, וממיתין אותו ברגל, umemisin oso baregel, and you execute him
on the רגל, regel, שנאמר וכל העם ישמעו ויראו ולא יזידון עוד.
shenemar vechol ha'am yishme'u veyira'u velo yezidun od. Everybody has to hear
and be afraid. This is again to protect the authority of the
בית דין Beis Din and that's why you do it on the
רגל regel and in the בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol to
emphasize their authority. דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי יהודה אומר
אין מענין את דינו של זה. Rabbi Yehuda omer ein me'anin es
dino shel ze. You do not postpone and cause עינוי הדין, inui
hadin, a suffering of the judgment of this person once there was
a גמר דין, gmar din, you do it immediately, you don't wait
for the רגל. regel. אלא ממיתין אותו מיד. ela memisin oso miyad.
Now presumably it would still be in the בית דין הגדול, Beis
Din Hagadol, not in his local city because he rebelled against the
בית
דין הגדול. Beis Din Hagadol. So but you do it immediately, but
you don't wait till the רגל. regel. וכותבין ושולחין שלוחין בכל המקומות.
vechosvin veshulchin sheluchin bechol hamakomos. איש פלוני מתחייב מיתה בבית דין. ish
ploni mischayev misa beveise din. But and then what do you do
with וכל העם ישמעו ויראו? vechol ha'am yishme'u veyira'u? You send out
messages to everybody, but you don't wait for everybody to gather. Okay,
so that's what you do.
But presumably again everything would be in the בית דין
הגדול. Beis Din Hagadol.
Now I should say that there's actually a difference between where he
gets executed and where his גמר דין gmar din is because interestingly,
even though all of this is challenging the authority of the בית
דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol, if you go back to the very
first משנה Mishnah of סנהדרין Sanhedrin of the things that require seventy-one,
you will see that it does not say that the judgment of
the זקן ממרא zaken mamre requires a בית דין Beis Din of
seventy-one, right? So it says and here it says he went back
to his city and he taught there. So actually רמב''ם Rambam makes
this explicit and רמב''ם Rambam actually says that the בית דין Beis
Din in his city will judge him as a זקן ממרא, zaken
mamre, but then from there he gets brought to
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So when ר' יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* says אין מענין את
דינו של זה *ein ma'anin es dino shel ze*,
so if his judgment was actually
in his local בית דין *Beis Din*, then they would be executed
in his local בית דין *Beis Din*. So I think I might
have said that a little bit incorrectly before. But anyway, so the
question is, he would be judged in his local בית דין *Beis
Din*, he'd go back locally, and then the question is now where
do you execute him? תנא tanna קמא *Tanna Kamma* says it would
be in the בית דין הגדול *Beis Din HaGadol*, and ר' יהודה
*Rebbi Yehuda* presumably would be in his local בית דין *Beis Din*,
but you would send out the messages everywhere. בכל מקום אף על
פי שנתחייב מיתה misah בבית דין *Be-chol makom, af al pi she-nis-chayev
misa be-veis din*. By the way, I should also say mentioning רמב"ם
Rambam *Rambam*, that רמב"ם *Rambam*, you know, deals with the whole idea
of this משנה mishnah. *Mishna* about לולב *Lulav*, you know, in this
discussion in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* as an add-on. He says, of
course, everything we said before that could lead to חייב כרת *chayav
kares* and חייב חטאת *chayav chatas* or whatever, that would all be
זקן ממרא *Zaken Mamre*. But if you have something that's not חייב
כרת *chayav kares* and not חייב חטאת *chayav chatas* but fits these
parameters here about מוסיף גורע *mosif gore'a*, then you're also זקן ממרא
*Zaken Mamre* for that. So it's like a single add-on. Anyway, let's
take a look at the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* now, פ"ט *pei-tes*. תנו
רבנן tanu rabanan, *Tanna Rabbanan*, Rabbis taught: אין ממיתין אותו לא בבית
דין שבעירו ולא בבית דין שביבנה *ein memisin oso, lo ve-veis din
she-be-iro ve-lo ve-veis din she-be-Yavneh*. You don't execute him in his local
בית דין *Beis Din* and not the one in יבנה *Yavneh*, אלא
מעלין אותו לבית דין הגדול שבירושלים ומשמרין אותו עד הרגל וממיתין אותו
ברגל *ela ma'alin oso le-veis din hagadol she-bi-Yerushalayim u-mish-marin oso ad ha-regel
u-memisin oso ba-regel*. שנאמר וכל העם ישמעו וייראו *Shenemar ve-chol ha-am yishme'u
ve-yira'u*, דברי ר' עקיבא *divrei Rebbi Akiva*.
Okay, pretty much exactly our משנה *Mishna*. You wait till the רגל
*regel* and you do it there. אמר לו amar lo, ר' יהודה
*Amar lo Rebbi Yehuda*, ר' יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* said to him: וכי
נאמר יראו וייראו *ve-chi ne'emar yir'u ve-yira'u*? Does it say that everybody
will see and fear, that everybody has to know about it through
directly witnessing it? והלא לא נאמר אלא ישמעו וייראו *Ve-halo lo ne'emar
ela yishme'u ve-yira'u*. They'll hear about it and fear. למה מענין את
דינו של זה *Lamma me'annin es dino shel ze*? So why would
you delay his judgment? אלא ממיתין אותו מיד *Ela, memisin oso mi-yad*.
You execute him immediately. And as we just discussed, that would mean
that you would do it even in his local בית דין *Beis
Din* where he was judged. וכותבין ושולחין בכל מקום איש פלוני נתחייב
מיתה בבית דין *Ve-kosvin u-sholchin be-chol makom: Ish ploni nis-chayev misa be-veis
din*. And then you would just send the messages out. תנו רבנן
*Tanna Rabbanan*, Rabbis taught: ארבעה צריכין הכרזה *arba'ah tzerichin achraza*. Four people
you have to announce throughout the land of Israel that they were
executed because it says explicitly in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*: וכל ישראל
ישמעו וייראו *ve-chol Yisrael yishme'u ve-yira'u*. המסית *Ha-meisis*, the one who seduces
to עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *avoda zara*, ובן סורר ומורה *u-ven sorer
u-moreh*, the בן סורר ומורה *ben sorer u-moreh*, זקן ממרא *zaken mamre*,
and עדים זוממין *edim zomemin*. All of them it says וכל ישראל
ישמעו וייראו *ve-chol Yisrael yishme'u ve-yira'u*. בכלו כתיב *Be-chullu kesiv*, as the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, בהו וכל העם *be-hu ve-chol ha-am* or וכל
ישראל *ve-chol Yisrael*. ובעדים זוממין *U-ve-edim zomemin*, the one exception is עדים
זוממין *edim zomemin*, כתיב והנשארים ישמעו וייראו *kesiv ve-hanish'arim yishme'u ve-yira'u*. דלאו
כל עמא חזו לסהדותא *De-lav kol amma chazu le-sahaduso*. It's not everybody
because not everyone can be an עד *ed*. So only the people
who are really taking heart are the people like who are כשר
*kosher* to be עדים *edim*, starting with
the men and whatever and not גזלנים *gazlanim*, etc., etc. Now of
course not everybody can be a בן סורר ומורה *ben sorer u-moreh*
either, but at least it means that people will be afraid of
parental authority. רמב"ן Ramban *Ramban* points out by the way that in
all of these cases, what's happening, this is רמב"ן על התורה *Ramban
al ha-Torah*, what's happening is that various institutions are being protected and
even the people are being executed even though the sin itself might
not be deserving of execution, they're being executed to protect these institutions
and that's why it says וכל ישראל ישמעו וייראו *ve-chol Yisrael yishme'u
ve-yira'u*. So the most obvious here, two of the things that we
often say, hey wait, what did they really do? בן סורר ומורה
*Ben sorer u-moreh*, which is protecting parental authority, and עדים זוממין *edim
zomemin*,
which
is protecting the integrity of the courts. So by עדים זוממין *edim
zomemin*, you know, the guy didn't actually get executed and they're getting
executed, but again that's וכל ישראל ישמעו וייראו *ve-chol Yisrael yishme'u ve-yira'u*.
We have to protect the integrity. זקן ממרא *Zaken Mamre* is the
authority also of like, you know, the deciding role of the courts,
not the adjudicating, but, you know, their authority to interpret, and
המסית *Ha-meisis*, of course, you know, God's authority, even if somebody doesn't
listen and nobody is עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah, *oveid avoda
zara*, they're undermining the divine authority. And that's why it says ישמעו
וייראו *yishme'u ve-yira'u*, but that's also why the punishment can be a
little disproportionate to the actual sin. Okay, let's take a look now
next משנה *Mishna*. נביא navi. השקר *Navi Ha-sheker*. Now we're moving on
from זקן ממרא *Zaken Mamre*. The next person of חנק chenek *chenek*
is נביא navi השקר *Navi Ha-sheker*. נביא navi השקר המתנבא מה שלא
שמע hamitnabe mah shelo shama, *Navi Ha-sheker ha-misnabei mah she-lo shama*, somebody
who prophesies something that they never heard, never got any prophecy about,
או מה שלא נאמר לו *o mah she-lo ne'emar lo*, or something
that was a prophecy given to his colleague, a different נביא navi
*navi*, and somehow he found out about it and then he went
around claiming that he had received that prophecy. Now technically that is
also in the category of מה שלא שמע *mah she-lo shama* because
he did not get that direct prophecy. But nevertheless we're saying even
though it was a prophecy that was given to his friend, he's
still חייב *chayav*. And that's basically the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*: אך הנביא
אשר יזיד לדבר דבר בשמי ach hanavi asher yazid ledaber davar bishmi,
את אשר לא צויתיו לדבר et asher lo tzivitiv ledaber, *ach ha-navi
asher yazid le-daber davar bi-shmi es asher lo tzivisiv le-daber*. there, right,
ואשר ידבר בשם אלהים אחרים, va'asher yedaber beshem elohim acherim, something I
did not command and who speaks in the name of other gods.
So that's the next one. So, מתנבא מה שלא שמע מה שלא
נאמר לו מיתתו בידי אדם. mitnabeh mah shelo shama mah shelo ne'emar
lo misato bidei adam. That is somebody that will be killed through
human agency,
right, ומת הנביא ההוא. umeis hanavi hahu. אבל הכובש נבואתו, aval hakoveish
nevuato, somebody that suppresses his נבואה, nevuah, and he received a prophecy
from God, but he is not going ahead and sharing it. והמותר
על דברי נביא, vehamavater al divrei navi, or somebody who violates the
word of a נביא. navi ונביא שעבר על דברי עצמו, venavi she'avar
al divrei atzmo, or he violated his own prophecy, okay, מיתתו בידי
שמים, misato bidei shamayim, that's left to God, שנאמר אנכי אדרש מעמו.
shene'emar anochi edrosh meimo. Okay, what the פסוק pasuk says, אשר לא
ישמע אל דברי. asher lo yishma el devarai. Okay, somebody who does
not listen to the words, I, God, will take care of him.
So we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara it's not somebody who doesn't
listen to the words of the נביא navi or אשר לא ישמיע,
asher lo yashmia, does not make them heard, the נביא navi who
does not express them, right? That's up to God.
המתנבא בשם עבודת כוכבים, hamitnabe beshem avodat kochavim, now let's say somebody
testifies in the name of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, right, ואשר ידבר
בשם אלהים אחרים, also in the פסוק, pasuk we'll say כך אמר
עבודת כוכבים, kach amar avodat kochavim, this is what this god said,
אפילו כיון את ההלכה לטמא את הטמא ולטהר את הטהור, afillu kivein
et hahalachah letame et hatame uletahar et hatahor, even if he's saying
this god said that you have to keep שבת Shabbos and here
are the thirty-nine מלאכות melachot etc., and this is what the, you
know, בעל Ba'al told me to tell all of you to do,
nevertheless, that is a case of a נביא שקר. navi sheker. All
right, now again, it's really still all in the category of giving
a נבואה nevuah that you did not hear from God. Okay, but
nevertheless, it's explained in the פסוק pasuk as a different category.
Now, הבא על אשת איש, haba al eishet ish, now we're totally
moving on. The final category or the penultimate category here of חנק
chenek. is somebody who has intercourse with a married woman, adultery.
כיון שנכנסה לרשות הבעל לנישואין, kivan shenichnasah lereshut haba'al lenisuin, once she
has gone under the into the husband's domain for the purpose of
חופה, chuppah, אף על פי שלא נבעלה, af al pi shelo nivalah,
even though she has not yet had sex, but once she's a
נשואה, nesuah,
then הבא עליה הרי זה בחנק. haba aleha harei zeh bichenek. Then
that makes her a married woman who is נשואה nesuah and the
punishment is חנק. chenek בת כהן
וזוממי בת כהן ובועלה, bat kohen uzomemei bat kohen uvo'alah, now, a
בת כהן bat kohen gets שרפה. sreifah. But it's remember, היא באש
תשרף, hi ba'esh tisaref, she and not בועלה, bo'alah, her husband only
gets חנק—only, chenek, whatever—but that's because for him, it's still, you know,
not her husband, excuse me, the person she had the affair with.
Okay, it's adultery, so he gets the standard punishment of adultery, חנק,
chenek, but only she gets
שרפה. sreifah. So, not only that, if people were found to be
עדים זוממים eidim zomemim trying to be מחייב mechayev her שרפה, sreifah,
because they are men and she's a woman, they would get the
punishment
that the lover would get, the adulterer would get, they get חנק,
chenek not
שרפה. sreifah. זוממי בת כהן ובועלה, zomemei bat kohen uvo'alah, so the
one who had sex with the בת כהן bat kohen or the
ones עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim, they also get חנק chenek. and not
שרפה. sreifah. But ultimately that boils down to the category of
adultery. שכל המוזממים מקדימים להם מיתה, shekol hamuzmamim makdimim lahem misah, anybody
who's עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim, they get right away get the מיתה
that they were trying to bring upon the other person, חוץ מזוממי
בת כהן ובועלה. chutz mizzomemei bat kohen uvo'alah. The one exception is
זוממי בת כהן, zomemei bat kohen, because it says היא באש תשרף,
hi ba'esh tisaref, only she gets שרפה, sreifah, all the men involved
in this would get חנק. Okay, let's see the גמרא. Gemara תנו
רבנן, שלשה מיתתן בידי אדם ושלשה מיתתן בידי שמים. sheloshah misatam bidei
adam vesheloshah misatam bidei shamayim. Three cases of the נביא navi get
it from by human agency, three through God.
המתנבא מה שלא שמע, ha-mitnabeh ma she-lo shama, somebody gives נבואה nevuah
from what he did not hear from God, ומה שלא נאמר לו,
umah shelo ne'emar lo, or was given to another נביא navi. but
not given to him, המתנבא בשם עבודת כוכבים, hamitnabe beshem avodat kochavim,
or in the name of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah? מיתתן בידי אדם,
misatan bidei adam, they get punished by human agency. הכובש נבואתו והמותר
על דברי נביא ונביא שעבר על דברי עצמו מיתתן בידי שמים. hakoveish
nevuato vehamavater al divrei navi venavi she'avar al divrei atzmo misatan bidei
shamayim. Okay, that's basically our משנה. מנא הני מילי, minani hanei milei,
where do we know this from? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב דאמר
קרא, amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav de'amar kra, the פסוק says, אך
הנביא אשר יזיד לדבר דבר בשמי, somebody who speaks in my name,
and then it says את אשר לא צויתיו לדבר, what I did
not command. זה מתנבא מה שלא שמע. zeh mitnabe mah shelo shama.
Okay, that he's doing it on his own, what he didn't hear.
ואשר לא צויתיו, va'asher lo tzivitiv, and that I did not command
him to speak, לחבירו צויתיו, lachaveiro tzivitiv, even if I commanded his
friend to speak it, since he wasn't commanded, that still makes him
a נביא שקר navi sheker because he's saying that he was given
that נבואה. nevuah. Okay, זה מתנבא מה שלא נאמר לו. zeh mitnabe
mah shelo ne'emar lo. Something that was said not said to him.
ואשר ידבר בשם אלהים אחרים זה מתנבא בשם עבודת כוכבים. va'asher yedaber
beshem elohim acherim zeh mitnabe beshem avodat kochavim. Okay, or in the
name of other gods. וכתיב ומת הנביא ההוא, uchtiv umeis hanavi hahu,
he will be put to death, וכל מיתה האמורה בתורה סתם אינה
אלא חנק, vechol misah ha'amurah batorah stam einah ela chenek, and סתם
מיתה stam misah is by strangulation. הכובש נבואתו והמותר על דברי נביא
ונביא שעבר על דברי עצמו—if hakoveish nevuato vehamavater al divrei navi venavi
she'avar al divrei atzmo somebody, you know, suppresses his נבואה nevuah or
violates the word of a נביא navi or a נביא navi who
violates his own words... He violated his own words, מיתתו בידי שמים,
mitato biydei shamayim, that is God brings about the death. דכתיב והאיש
אשר לא ישמע את דברי את דברי, de-chtiv ve-ha-ish asher lo yishma
et devarai et devarai, anyway, the man who does not hear. וקרי
ביה לא ישמיע, ve-kari beih lo yashmia, read it "does not make
heard", so he does not go out and preach my word. וקרי
ביה לא ישמע, ve-kari beih lo yishma, does not hear, he himself
does not obey
את דברי. et devarai. וכתיב אנכי אדרש מעמו, u-chtiv anochi edrosh mi-imo,
I will seek it out בידי שמים. biydei shamayim. So if you
suppress your own נבואה nevuah or you violate or somebody else violates
the נבואה, nevuah, then that is God will take care of that.
Now we're going to go through these individually. המתנבא מה שלא שמע,
somebody who testifies what they did not hear, כגון צדקיה בן כנענה,
kegon Tzidkiyah ben Kena'anah, like צדקיה בן כנענה. Tzidkiyah ben Kena'anah. דכתיב
ויעש לו צדקיה בן כנענה קרני ברזל, de-chtiv vaya'as lo Tzidkiyah ben
Kena'anah karnei barzel, and he made these horns and he said כה
תנגח את ארם. ko tenagach et Aram. Okay, but that was because
God, a
false spirit told him this testimony. So the גמרא's Gemara going to
say
מאי הוה ליה למיעבד? mai hava leh le-me'evad? But wait, how? He
wasn't to blame. He actually received some visitation, some vision and that
made him believe he had received a נבואה. nevuah. ורוח נבות אתא
אתיי, ve-ruach Navot ata itey, the spirit of נבות, Navot, נבות היזרעאלי
Navot ha-Yizre'eli that was murdered by אחאב, Ach'av, his spirit came back
to cause this נביא navi, to err because ultimately it was to
get אחאב Ach'av to, as we'll see in a minute, what the
פסוקים, psukim, to fall in battle. So how can you blame
צדקיה? Tzidkiyah? He thought he was receiving a נבואה. nevuah. דכתיב, de-chtiv,
now we're going to give the context. ויאמר ה' מי יפתה את
אחאב ויעל ויפל ברמת גלעד, vayomer Hashem mi yefateh et Ach'av ve-ya'al
ve-yipol be-Ramot Gil'ad, God said who will seduce אחאב Ach'av and he
will go up and fall in רמת גלעד Ramot Gil'ad in battle?
ויצא הרוח ויעמד לפני ה' ויאמר אני אפתנו, vayetzei ha-ruach va-ya'amod lifnei
Hashem va-yomer ani afatenu, some spirit came and stood before God and
said I will seduce him. ויאמר תפתה וגם תוכל צא ועשה כן,
vayomer tefateh ve-gam tuchal tzei va-asei chen, seduce him and be successful,
go and do this. Okay, and then this spirit went and came
to
צדקיה בן כנענה Tzidkiyah ben Kena'anah and gave him this נבואה, nevuah,
so he thought it was a genuine נבואה nevuah from God, but
it was not. It was this false spirit. It was actually interesting
God even allowed the false spirit to go. Okay, and the נבואה
nevuah was go to war, you'll be successful, and in the end
it was to deceive him and he fell in battle. אמר
רב יהודה amar Rav Yehuda מאי צא? mai tzei? What does צא
tzei mean? צא ממחיצתי, tzei me-mechitzati, leave my quarters, leave my domain,
because which is again maybe trying to deal with the idea that
God is allowing it to do, encouraging it to do, but it's
not coming from God, it's actually a false נבואה. nevuah. מאי רוח?
mai ruach? Now what was this רוח? ruach? אמר רבי יוחנן amar
Rabbi Yochanan רוח של נבות היזרעאלי הוה. ruach shel Navot ha-Yizre'eli hava.
So נבות היזרעאלי, Navot ha-Yizre'eli, it was the spirit of נבות היזרעאלי
Navot ha-Yizre'eli that אחאב Ach'av had killed and he was now using
the opportunity to go have אחאב Ach'av fall in battle which God
sort of had wanted to happen, but it was a false נבואה
nevuah because it was telling אחאב Ach'av you should go fight and
you'll be successful. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says okay, so
צדקיה's Tzidkiyah giving this נבואה nevuah and it wasn't from God, but
how could you punish him? He thought he was a genuine, honest,
real נביא. navi So the גמרא Gemara says,
where was he? So the גמרא Gemara says no, הוה ליה למידע,
hava leh le-meda, צדקיה Tzidkiyah should have paid attention, should have been
careful to רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak because he should have followed the
teaching of רבי יצחק. Rabbi Yitzchak. דאמר רבי יצחק de-amar Rabbi Yitzchak
סגנון אחד עולה לכמה נביאים, signon echad oleh le-chama nevi'im, one type
of theme,
content, vision,
is given to many prophets, ואין שני נביאים מתנבאים בסגנון אחד, ve-ein
shnei nevi'im mitnab'im be-signon echad, but two prophets never exactly give the
same נבואה nevuah in the exact same language. So סגנון signon here
it's used different ways. In the first way it sort of means
the content, like one idea can be given to multiple prophets, but
ואין שני נביאים מתנבאים בסגנון אחד, ve-ein shnei nevi'im mitnab'im be-signon echad,
that's like a common phrase which is people say things, they articulate
the same idea in different ways. Okay, so nobody would have said
the exact same words. Each נביא navi, goes so it gets refracted
through the נביא's navi own lens and intellect and each one gets
expressed in a unique way. Okay, so where do you see this?
עובדיה אמר Ovadia amar זדון לבך השיאך, zdon libcha hishi'acha, עובדיה Ovadia
said the brazenness of your heart or whatever has misled you. ירמיה
אמר Yirmiyah amar תפלצתך השיאה אותך זדון לבך, tiflatzecha hisiah otach zdon
libcha, okay, almost the same thing, זדון לבך השיאך zdon libcha hishi'acha
etc., but slightly different phrasing. So you should have known and what
was happening here was that all of the נביאים nevi'im who were
saying this were saying it in the exact same language. והני מדי
קאמרי כולהו כחדא, ve-hani midei ka-amrei kulehu k-achada, and in this case
since all the נביאים nevi'im at this time were saying the exact
same language. והני מדי קאמרי כולהו כחדא, ve-hani midei ka-amrei kulehu k-achada,
and in this case since all the נביאים nevi'im at this time
were saying the exact same. same words, שמע מינה לא כלום קאמרי
shma mina lo klum kaamrei they should have realized that they were
not really getting a true prophecy because everybody was saying the exact
same words. So the גמרא Gemara, for once challenges the, what do
you call it, the anachronism and says דילמא לא הוה ידע ליה
להא דרבי יצחק, dilma lo hava yada lei l'ha d'Rabbi Yitzchak, maybe
they didn't know רבי יצחק's Rabbi Yitzchak teaching. How did they, what
were they supposed to know that when everybody is saying the exact
same thing it's not a true prophecy? So the גמרא Gemara says
יהושפט הוה התם. Yehoshaphat hava hatam. No, יהושפט Yehoshaphat was there וכאמר
להו v'ka'amar lehu and he was telling them that what they were
saying wasn't true prophecy דכתיב ויאמר יהושפט. d'chtiv vayomer Yehoshaphat. And יהושפט
Yehoshaphat said האין פה נביא לה' עוד? ha'ein po navi l'Hashem od?
Is there no other true נביא, navi you know, of God here?
So, so אמר ליה היכא כל הני. amar lei heicha kol hanei.
So, so they said what do you mean? All these people, they're
prophets of God, why are you not accepting their prophecy? They're telling
אחאב Achav to go testify. So אמר ליה amar lei he said
כך מקובלני מבית אבי אבא, kach mekubbani mibeis avi abba, this is
the tradition I have from my father's father's house. סגנון אחד עולה
לכמה נביאים ואין שני נביאים מתנבאים בסגנון אחד. signon echad oleh l'chama
neviim v'ein shenei neviim mitnab'im b'signon echad. Okay, so presumably since יהושפט
Yehoshaphat was challenging them and the גמרא Gemara is now reading in
that he was telling them you can't be receiving true prophecy because
you would not be saying the right thing, the same thing, they
should have known and realized what they were saying was not true
prophecy. Now it still raises a question like okay, but is that
going to make them מזיד maysid and חייב מיתה? chayav misa? Like
I believe that I really had this, like because I should have
realized logically. My experience was some spirit came and filled me and
made me believe I had this prophecy to give over. You know,
it's really unclear here in this גמרא, Gemara's but if I should
have known logically based on the rule it couldn't be true, but
I was still saying it, I should have realized that I was
saying over a prophecy that wasn't from God. That's what it seems
to be saying. All right anyway, but that's an example of somebody
who says a prophecy not from God. The easier examples you just
סתם stam make it
up. Okay. המתנבא מה שלא נאמר לו, hamitnabe mah shelo ne'emar lo,
something that wasn't said to you but was said to somebody else,
כגון חנניה בן עזור k'gon Chananya ben Azur דקאי ירמיה בשוקא עילאה.
d'ka'i Yirmiyah b'shuka ila'ah. חנניה בן עזור Chananya ben Azur that ירמיהו
Yirmiyahu was at the upper marketplace וקאמר כה אמר ה' צבאות הנני
שובר את קשת עילם. v'ka'amar koh amar Hashem Tzeva'os hineni shover es
keshes Elam. I will break the, you know,
the bow of עילם, Elam, which is one of the nations that
came together with
בבל. Bavel. נשא חנניה קל וחומר בעצמו. nasa Chananya kal vachomer b'atzmo.
So חנניה Chananya made a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה עילם שלא בא אלא לעזור בבל. umah
Elam shelo ba ela la'azor Bavel. עילם Elam that is coming only
to help בבל Bavel to destroy Israel, אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא הנני
שובר את קשת עילם. amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu hineni shover es keshes
Elam. I'm going to break their strength. כשדים עצמם, Kasdim atzmam, the
כשדים, Kasdim, the, you know, themselves על אחת כמה וכמה, al achas
kama v'kama, how much more so will God visit punishment on them?
ואזא איהו בשוקא תתאה ואמר, v'aza ihu b'shuka tata'ah v'amar,
and he said כה אמר ה' שברתי את עול מלך בבל. koh
amar Hashem shavarti es ol melech Bavel. I will break the yoke
of בבל. Bavel. So there, even though that was reasonable to think
that that's what God wished and would have said or whatever, he
did not receive that prophecy. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה
רב פפא לאביי amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye הא לחבריה נמי לא
נאמר? ha l'chavreih nami lo ne'emar? That's not exactly the case because
we're talking about a case where you say something that you didn't
hear but your colleague heard. Here, ירמיה Yirmiyah didn't hear that at
all. ירמיה Yirmiyah just heard about עילם. Elam. אז אמר ליה כיון
דאיתיהיב ליה קל וחומר למידרש, az amar lei keivan d'isyahiv lei kal
vachomer l'midrash, look,
you're able to make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Again, I don't
know exactly about קל וחומר kal vachomer at historical events and what's
going to happen in the future, but okay. But since that's, you
know, that's the קל וחומר kal vachomer is a legitimate one, כמאן
דאיתמר ליה דמי. k'man d'is'mar lei dami. So it's as if it
was said to ירמיה Yirmiyah that God will destroy not only עילם
Elam but also בבל. Bavel. That stands completely totally reason. So I
don't know, and if ירמיה Yirmiyah would have said God said בבל
Bavel would be destroyed, that would have been okay, not clear. Okay,
but it sounds like it. But because he now said it as
if he had heard it,
that makes it,
חנניה Chananya said it as if he had heard it, that makes
him a נביא שקר navi sheker because it was not said to
him even if it was effectively said to ירמיה. Yirmiyah. Okay, הוא
ניהו דלא
נאמר לו, hu nihu d'lo ne'emar lo, it wasn't said to him.
המתנבא בשם עבודה זרה, hamitnabe b'shem avodah zarah, now what's a case
of עבודה זרה? כגון נביאי הבעל, k'gon nevi'ei haba'al, that's easy, like
the נביאים neviim of the בעל. ba'al. Now again, all those sort
of fall under the category of לא נאמר לו. lo ne'emar lo.
הכובש את נבואתו, hakovesh es nevu'aso,
somebody who suppresses his נבואה, nevuah, כגון k'gon last line here of
פ"ט עמוד א. peih tes amud alef. יונה בן אמיתי, Yonah ben
Amittai, יונה, Yonah, the prophet יונה Yonah who ran away rather than
to give his
prophecy. והמוותר על דברי נביא, v'hamavater al divrei navi, somebody who violates
what the נביא navi says, כגון k'gon top of פ"ט עמוד ב,
peih tes amud beis, for
example חברי דמיכה, chavrei d'Micha, the colleagues of מיכה. Micha. דכתיב ואיש
אחד מבני הנביאים אמר אל רעהו
בדבר ה' הכיני נא, d'chtiv v'ish echad mibnei hanevi'im amar el re'eihu
bidvar Hashem hakeini na, or the friend of, not
friends. So one person said to his fellow, you know, smite me,
and we have a tradition that this was מיכה. Micha. מיכה Micha
was saying it and he was doing this in order that he
should look beaten up and then he was going to go to
אחאב Achav and use it to give a message to אחאב. Achav.
Okay, but so here a נביא, navi מיכה, Micha, said to this
person beat me up, hit me, וימאן האיש להכותו vayi'maen ha'ish lehakoto
and he refused, even though the נביא navi told him to do
it. וכתיב ויאמר לו יען אשר לא שמעת u'chesiv vayomer lo ya'an
asher lo shamata because you did not listen, so blah blah blah
and then in the end it says that a lion came out
and ate him and consumed him and he died. That was God,
you know, God אנוכי אדרוש מעמו, anochi edrosh mi'imo, because he violated
what the נביא navi said. נביא שעבר על דברי עצמו, navi she'avar
al divrei atzmo, what's a case of a נביא navi violating his
own words? כגון עדו הנביא, kegon Ido HaNavi, דכתיב כי כן ציווה
אותי d'chesiv ki chen tziva osi because by עדו הנביא Ido HaNavi
he says, you know, that he went and he said to this
person, you know, God has commanded me you should not eat bread
and you should not drink water, and this person says ויאמר לו
גם אני נביא כמוך, vayomer lo gam ani navi kamocha, but what
do you mean? I'm a נביא navi like you and I say
it is okay to eat and drink. וכתיב וישב איתו u'chesiv vayeshev
ito
and this עדו הנביא Ido HaNavi even though he knew better from
God, he went ahead and he listened to this other person who
also claimed to be a נביא navi and he ate and he
drank. וכתיב וילך וימצאהו אריה, u'chesiv vayelech vayimtza'ehu aryeh, another case of
another lion finding him and destroying him. So he violated his own
word and he was eaten by a lion as was the first
case of also this מיכה, Micha, this person who wouldn't hit מיכה
Micha and he was eaten by a lion and
יונה Yonah was swallowed by a whale but eventually of course or
no not a whale excuse me a fish eventually got saved. Okay,
תני תנא קמיה דרב חסדא, tani tanna kamaye d'Rav Chisda, תנא learned
in front of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. הכובש נבואתו לוקה, hakovesh nevu'aso
lokeh,
if somebody holds back his נבואה, nevu'ah, he gets מלקות, malkus, okay?
Because you know, because first of all you have to get the
לאו lav of what exactly but before you get to pointing out
what פסוק you're violating, he said a better question. He said אמר
ליה מאן דאכל תמרי בארבי לא לקי. amar lei man de'achal tamre
b'arba lo lakei.
So according to you,
if somebody were to eat dates in a sieve, that's an ארבי,
arba, would he get מלקות? malkus? But that's the way רש״י Rashi
explains it, but it's better to read that this ארבי arba is
just some like distant location, like it's saying if somebody eats dates
in the middle of a forest, like would he get מלקות? malkus?
Nobody would know about it. So
whatever
it was it was some idiom but basically it means how can
you give testimony that this guy suppressed his נבואה? nevu'ah? How are
somebody supposed to know and to warn him? Besides the fact that
it's a passive, he's not doing anything active, besides the fact we'd
have to find the לאו lav that he's over. Okay, fine, but
anyway how could anybody even give him warning? מאן מתרי ביה, man
masri bei, who can warn him? אמר אביי
חברי נביאי, amar Abaye chavrei nevi'ei, so his colleagues נביאים, nevi'im, they
would know that he received the נבואה. nevu'ah. מנא ידעי, mina yada'i,
how do they know? אמר אביי דכתיב כי לא יעשה השם אלוקים
דבר כי אם גילה סודו, amar Abaye d'chesiv ki lo ya'aseh Hashem
Elokim davar ki im gila sodo, you know, God will never you
know do something unless he has revealed his secret to the
נביאים. nevi'im. So understand that to mean that like he wouldn't tell
one נביא navi something unless he told another נביא navi so somebody
else knows about this.
Okay, which is also still pretty interesting, it's sort of not publicly
available information,
you know how you can sort of trust somebody to testify I
knew through a נבואה nevu'ah this and therefore I warned him that
he had received it. All right, anyway,
ודילמא הדר ביה, v'dilma hadar bei, maybe the God reversed himself? And
this is a whole question, right, about how do you know like
if a נביא Navi predicts something is going to happen and it
doesn't happen because God sometimes reverses himself when people do תשובה? teshuva?
So a whole complicated issue, but anyway maybe God reversed himself so
maybe the reason the נביא Navi did not give this prophecy assuming
it was a prophecy of doom or of punishment was because God
had retracted it. No, אם איתא דהדר ביה אודועי הוה מודעי לכולהו
נביאי. im isah de'hadar bei, oduey hava modie l'kula nevi'ei. No,
if it had been retracted then all the נביאים nevi'im who knew
that it had been given would also know that it had been
retracted. והא יונה דהדר ביה ולא אודועי הוה, v'ha'Yonah de'hadar bei v'lo
odu'ei hu, wait
a minute, יונה Yonah was, you know, it was retracted but he
wasn't informed because it says that יונה Yonah went outside to see
what was going to happen. So how so you see it could
be a prophecy could be given and retracted without the person being
informed, without the נביא Navi being informed? גמרא Gemara says no, מעיקרא
נינוה נהפכת אמרי ליה, me'ikara ninveh nehepaches amarei lei,
originally God said נינוה Ninveh would be overturned. איהו לא ידע אי
לטובה אי לרעה, ihu lo yada, ee l'tova ee l'ra,
but יונה Yonah didn't you know could have interpreted it either way.
יונה Yonah didn't know, did it mean they'll overturn their deeds and
they'll do תשובה teshuva or it will be destroyed. So it wasn't
an actual retraction, now there was greater clarity into what that original
prophecy had actually meant. Anyway, fascinating idea that you could imagine that
you could give somebody התראה hatra'ah because you happen to know the
נבואה nevu'ah that that person received. Anyway, fascinating. But also fascinating גמרא
assumption that if one נביא Navi knows something other נביאים nevi'im know
something and the idea also that sometimes נבואה, nevu'ah, you know, prophecies
are retracted once people do תשובה. teshuva. All right, so now גמרא
continues. המוותר על דברי נביא, HaMivater al divrei Navi,
somebody, now we're going to get to a really interesting question is
how do you know somebody is really a נביא Navi that you
have an obligation to listen to them. Somebody who violates the words
of a נביא Navi. gets punished by God, מיתה בידי שמים. misah
bi-yedei shamayim. מנא ידעי דעניש? mina yeda'i de-anish? How do you know
that how do you know that this guy's really a נביא Navi.
that you should be punished for not listening to them? I mean,
look, we just had before the guy said hit me, you know?
I don't want to hit you. So how do you know the
guy's a נביא Navi, that you're supposed to listen to him? דייב
ליה אות, di-yahev lei os, that he gives you a sign. So
really what the גמרא is saying is here what proves how do
you know you know how do you prove that somebody is a
נביא Navi. with the halachic implications of then you have an obligation
to listen to him. So he gives you a sign which is
what the תורה Torah says ונתן אליך, ve-nasan elecha, right? So okay.
והיכא דלא יהב ליה אות ועניש? ve-heicha de-la yehav lei os ve-anish?
I mean, the problem תורה Torah says that if somebody gives you
a sign and he tells you to be עובד עבודה זרה, you
don't listen to it, but if he gives you a sign, you
should assume he you should assume and it comes true you should
assume that he's a true נביא. Navi? והיכא דלא יהב ליה אות
ועניש, ve-heicha de-la yehav lei os ve-anish,
but in the case of מיכה Michah where he said hit me,
you know, he didn't give him a sign to show this guy
that he was a true נביא. Navi, היכא דמוחזק שאני. heicha de-muchzak
shani. Oh,
if the guy is known to be a נביא, Navi, that's different.
Then he doesn't have to give you a sign when he tells
you to do something, he's already established himself as a נביא. So
what establishes somebody as a נביא? So if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, רש"י Rashi says היכא דהוחזק דצדיק ונביא אמת, heicha de-huchzak de-tzaddik
ve-navi emes,
that he's righteous and a נביא אמת. navi emes. How do you
know that he's a נביא אמת? navi emes? Because in the past
he's been saying things and they've been coming true. Okay. Now is
that the same as a sign? You know, is a sign something
that's wondrous and that's not the normal acts of nature? But if
somebody says, you know, tomorrow this stock is going to go up
two points and it goes up two points, is that, you know,
like and he predicts the future, is that constitute a sign or
not? Not clear. But anyway, but רש"י Rashi also says that you
know you know he's a צדיק, tzaddik, and that's an interesting question.
רמב"ם also deals with this. How much is it about the person's
character that's considered מוחזק muchzak and how much is it that the
person has already done and prophesied things that have come true and
actually demonstrated that they're a נביא, maybe without what would technically be
called a sign? All right, so a lot of interesting questions open
for interpretation here. ואי
לא תימא הכי, ve-ei lo teima hachi, because if you don't say
that, אברהם בהר המוריה היכא שמע ליה יצחק? Avraham be-Har HaMoriah heicha
shama lei Yitzchak? How did יצחק Yitzchak listen to אברהם Avraham and
agree to allow himself get slaughtered? Now if you just think about
that, אברהם Avraham definitely gets the צדיק tzaddik category, you know? Does
he get the אות os category? Not exactly clear. I mean, you
know, when did אברהם Avraham ever give a sign? When did אברהם
Avraham ever exactly prophesy about the future? But you certainly knew that
God was with אברהם. Avraham. I mean, so it raises really interesting
questions. אליהו בהר הכרמל היכא סמכי עליה ועבדי שחוטי חוץ? Eliyahu be-Har
HaKarmel heicha samchi alei ve-avdi shechutei chutz? How about אליהו? Eliyahu? He
told them actually violate an איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraisa and bring a
קרבן korban outside of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash when he was
showing up the נביאי הבעל. neviai ha-Ba'al. How did they listen to
him? אלא היכא דמוחזק שאני. ela heicha de-muchzak shani. If somebody is
מוחזק muchzak as a נביא, okay, as somebody who regularly is in
communication with God, you know, then that's different. But again, it sort
of begs the question what establishes that. ויהי אחר. vayehi achar.
Now since we mentioned the עקידה, Akeidah, now we're going to digress
a little and talk about the עקידה. Akeidah. ויהי אחר הדברים האלה
והאלהים נסה את אברהם. vayehi achar hadevarim ha-eileh ve-ha-Elokim nissah es Avraham.
It was after these things God tested אברהם. Avraham. אמר ר' יוחנן
משום ר' יוסי בן זמרא, amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yosi ben
Zimra, what's after what things? אחר דבריו של שטן. achar devarav shel
Satan. After the words of the שטן. Satan. דכתיב ויגדל הילד ויגמל
ויעש אברהם משתה גדול ביום הגמל את יצחק. de-kesiv vayigdal hayeled vayigamel
vaya'as Avraham mishteh gadol be-yom higamel es Yitzchak. He made a big
feast. אמר שטן לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar Satan lifnei ha-Kadosh Baruch
Hu, רבונו של עולם, Ribono shel Olam, זקן זה חננתו למאה שנה
פרי בטן, zaken zeh chanan-to le-me'ah shanah peri beten,
this old man that you after a hundred years have finally given
him, you know, the fruit of his womb. מכל סעודה שעשה לא
היה לו תור אחד או גוזל אחד להקריב לפניך. mikol seudah she-asah
lo hayah lo tor echad o gozal echad le-hakriv lefanecha. From all
the meals that he made, he didn't have one like turtledove, you
know, one one little bird to offer for you as a קרבן,
korban, which is interesting. We don't see that he did that. So
so how can you know what's going on here? He's not showing
proper gratitude. אמר לו, amar lo, God said to the שטן, Satan,
כלום עשה אלא בשביל בנו. kelum asah ela bishvil beno. See, look,
he's doing this whole feast for the sake of his son. To
show you how much אברהם Avraham values me, it's not a question
of would he offer up a little קרבן korban for me, but
אם אני אומר לו זבח את בנך
לפני, im ani omer lo zevach es bincha lefanai, slaughter your son
for me as a קרבן, korban, and he's doing all this for
his son. If I even ask him for his son, מיד זובחו,
mi-yad zovcho, he would immediate immediately agree to do it. מיד והאלהים
נסה את אברהם. mi-yad ve-ha-Elokim nissah es Avraham. God tested אברהם. Avraham.
I'm not going to get into the obvious theological issues here of
who is God trying to prove this to. רמב"ן says God doesn't
need to prove anything to God's self, this is mostly to prove
to
to actualize the potential that אברהם Avraham has. But but the מדרש
Midrash here is making God showing up the שטן. Satan. ויאמר *Vayomer*
קח נא את בנך *kach na et bincha*. אמר *Amar* רבי שמעון
בן אבא *Rabbi Shimon ben Abba* אין נא אלא לשון בקשה *ein
na ella lashon bakasha*. נא *Na* means please. משל למלך בשר ודם
*mashal lemelech basar vadam* שאמר עליו *she'amar alav* שעמדו עליו *she'amdu alav*
שעמדו עליו מלחמות הרבה *she'amdu alav milchamot harbeh*. There was like a
king that had a lot of wars. והיה לו גיבור אחד *vehaya
lo gibbor echad* and he had one major, you know,
hero,
valorous soldier, ונצחן *venatzchan* and he was able to win all the
wars. לימים עמדה עליו מלחמה חזקה *leyamim amda alav milchama chazaka* and
then there was like a extremely difficult war that came. אמר לו
amar lo, בבקשה ממך *amar lo bevakasha mimcha* and he said to
his general, "Please, עמוד לי במלחמה זו *amod li bemilchama zu*, I
need, you know, this stand up to me for this war. שלא
יאמרו ראשונות אין בהם ממש *shelo yomru rishonot ein bahem mamash*, so
people shouldn't say, 'Hey, the easier wars, those were easy, that what
the general was able to do, but you know and it doesn't
prove anything, he couldn't do the real difficult war.'" אף הקדוש ברוך
הוא אמר לאברהם *af hakadosh baruch hu amar le'avraham*, God said to
אברהם Avraham *Avraham*, "נסיתיך בכמה נסיונות *nisiticha bekamma nisyonot*, I have tested
you with many tests, ועמדת בכולן *ve'amadta bekullan*, you've succeeded in all
of them. עכשיו עמוד לי בנסיון זה *achshav amod li benisayon ze*,
but now please, here's going to be the hardest one and I
need you to pass it. שלא יאמרו אין ממש בראשונים *shelo yomru
ein mamash berishonim*, so people should not dismiss everything that you have
done prior to this." Okay, so that's קח נא *kach na*. את
בנך *et bincha*,
your son. שני בנים יש לי *shenei vanim yesh li*, this is
the famous רש"י *Rashi*, you know, quotes this, "Your son." אברהם Avraham
*Avraham* said back, "I have two sons, ישמעאל Yishmael *Yishmael* and יצחק
Yitzchak *Yitzchak*." את יחידך *et yechidecha*, no, no, your only son. זה
יחיד לאמו וזה יחיד לאמו *ze yachid le'immo veze yachid le'immo*, each
one is unique to his mother. אשר אהבת *asher ahavta*, the one
you love. תרוייהו רחמינא עליהון *teravyehu rachmina aleihon*, I love both of
them. It's really beautiful because you see that about how אברהם Avraham
*Avraham* loves ישמעאל Yishmael *Yishmael* and how difficult it is for אברהם
Avraham *Avraham* to send ישמעאל Yishmael *Yishmael* out. Okay. So then it
finally says, את יצחק Yitzchak, *et Yitzchak*. Fine, יצחק Yitzchak. *Yitzchak*. וכל
כך למה *vechol kach lamma*,
why did God build it up? Why didn't he just say קח
את יצחק Yitzchak *kach et Yitzchak*? וכל כך למה *vechol kach lamma*,
כדי שלא תטרף דעתו עליו *kedai shelo titaref da'ato alav*, so in
order that אברהם Avraham *Avraham* should not be overwhelmed by the shock,
you know, this gives אברהם *Avraham* time to acclimate to what God
is going to ask him. Okay. קדם שטן Satan לדרך *kiddem satan
laderech*. Now the שטן Satan *Satan*, as אברהם *Avraham* started taking יצחק
Yitzchak, *Yitzchak* to הר מוריה *Har Moriah*, the שטן Satan *Satan* sort
of jumped in front of him. אמר לו *amar lo* and said
to him, הנסה דבר אליך תלאה *hanissa davar eleicha tileh*, this is
from איוב *Iyov*, "Will he test you on a matter and you
will grow weary? הנה יסרת רבים וידיים רפות תחזק *hinneh yissarta rabbim
veyadayim rafot techazzek*, behold you have warned many
and you have strengthened weak hands. כושל יקימון מילך *koshel yekimun milecha*,
your words have lifted up those that would stumble. כי עתה תבוא
אליך ותלאה *ki atta tavo eleicha vetileh*, now comes to you and
you will weary?" So this is what, you know, one of איוב's
*Iyov's* colleagues were saying to him. "You have always been such a
strong source of faith for other people. Now that you've been challenged,
how can you let yourself, you know, stumble?" That was the פשט
*pshat* of the פסוק *pasuk*. But the way the גמרא *gemara* is
reading it is the following: is that he basically said to him,
the way רש"י *Rashi* understands this is he said that, אמר לו
*amar lo*, after you have been so strong and strengthened so many
people, הנסה *hanissa* like ויהי אחרי הנסות את אברהם *vayehi acharei hanassot
et avraham*, God should test you with this thing and make you
weary and give you this terrible, you know, test that demands so
much from you, especially after everything you've done for everyone else? Okay.
And like רש"י *Rashi* says, it will like destroy your children. Okay.
So how could God do this thing to you? You know what
also is possible you could also say is, is that you have
strengthened everybody with the idea of belief in God and morality and
so on, and now by putting this on you, it's going to
undermine the way all the ethical teachings that you've been bringing to
the world. אמר לו *amar lo*, אברהם *Avraham* said back to him,
אני בתומי אלך *ani betummi elech*, I don't ask questions. God asks
me, I'm doing it. You're right, it doesn't make sense, sort of
like the opposite of איוב *Iyov*, rather than challenge, I will just
accept and do what God has asked me. אמר לו *amar lo*,
so now going back to the פסוקים *psukim* to the פסוק *pasuk*
from איוב *Iyov*, הלא יראתך כסלתך *halo yiratcha kislatecha*, behold your fear
is your foolishness. You know, you're saying that you're being ירא אלוקים
*yere elokim*, you're really just being foolish. אמר לו *amar lo*, he
said back to him, זכור נא מי הוא נקי אבד *zechor na
mi hu naki avad*, "Know who is, you know, innocent that is
destroyed?" Meaning, so I just have to accept whatever God's judgment is.
וכיון דחזא דלא קא שמע ליה *vekeivan dechaza dela ka shema leh*,
once the שטן Satan *Satan* saw that he was not being successful
persuading אברהם *Avraham*, אמר לו *amar lo*, ואלי דבר יגונב *ve'elai davar
yugunav*,
"I had this thing was like stolen thing, you know, this like
I got this secret message," said the שטן *Satan*. כך שמעתי מאחורי
הפרגוד *kach shamati me'achorei hapargod*, "this is what I heard from behind
the curtain. השה לעולה ואין יצחק Yitzchak, לעולה *hasseh le'olah ve'ein yitzchak
le'olah*, that God isn't really even going to ask you for יצחק
Yitzchak *Yitzchak*, He's really just going to ask you to bring a
sheep." sheep. So maybe that also he was saying that to undermine
אברהם because now אברהם would do it just believing he wasn't really
being asked to bring יצחק Yitzchak and it would not be the
same succeeding in the test. So he was trying to sort of,
you know, sort of ruin, ruin the surprise but undermine the value
of the, of the test. And אברהם said back to him, אמר
לו, כך עונשו של בדאי, kach onsho shel badai, you know what
he said like maybe you're right but who knows, this is the
punishment that the liar gets, אפילו אומר אמת אין שומעין לו, afilu
omer emet ein shom’in lo, even if you're telling the truth, nobody
believes you anymore. I believe God has asked me for יצחק, Yitzchak
I'm going to listen to God, I'm not going to listen to
all the things that you are saying. You know נחמה ליבוביץ Nechama
Leibowitz by the way has a beautiful interpretation and she says that
the שטן in this case, and there's another similar מדרש Midrash where
the שטן says people are going to call you a murderer, you
know, how could God really be asking you, that this is the
מדרש Midrash sort of giving אברהם's own inner turmoil and inner conflict
and making it like externalizing it, and that the שטן is representing
the ways that אברהם himself is grappling and struggling, which makes it
much more powerful. I mean, if it was not a test, if
he wouldn't have had doubts and grappling, right, would it have been
a test at all is a question that needs to be asked.
Okay, let's just read a little more. רבי לוי אומר, Rabbi Levi
omer, it's not
אחר הדברים achar hadevarim that means the word of the שטן but
אחר דבריו של ישמעאל, achar devarav shel Yishmael, after the words of
ישמעאל Yishmael to יצחק. אמר לו
ישמעאל
ליצחק, amar lo Yishmael leYitzchak, ישמעאל said to יצחק on the day
that you know, you know, that they made this whole party for
יצחק, אני גדול ממך במצוות, ani gadol mimcha bamitzvot, that I am
better than you, שאתה מלת בן שמונת ימים, she’ata malta ben shmonat
yamim, maybe it wasn't on the day of the weaning but whatever,
here's what ישמעאל said, you know, you got your ברית מילה bris
milah eight days old, ואני בן שלוש עשרה שנה, va’ani ben shalosh
esre shana, I was thirteen, אמר לו, ישמעאל said to him, ובעבר
אחד אתה מגבה? uve’ever echad ata megaveh?
You're trying to show me how much, you know, better you are
than me because of one limb that you were willing to, you
know, undergo a difficult procedure for? אם אומר לי הקדוש ברוך הוא,
im omer li Hakadosh Baruch Hu, if God would say to me,
זבח עצמך לפני, zaveach atzmecha lefanai, offer yourself before Me, אני זובח,
ani zoveach, I would agree to it. מיד והאלקים נסה את אברהם.
miyad VeHaElokim nisa et Avraham. Now what's nicer about this one is
that it gets, you know, יצחק, I mean, it deals with the
whole problem. אברהם is being tested, יצחק is losing his life, where
is יצחק in this whole story? So here it brings in יצחק
as a subject as well. Okay, we will end with this for
now.